give us from the and good satanic I call
disenchantment because these five things
when developed and cultivated lead
exclusively to disenchantment to
dispassion to cessation to peace to
direct knowledge to enlightenment to
Nibbana what five here at bhiku dwells
contemplating the unattractiveness of
the body perceiving the repulsiveness of
food receiving non delight in the entire
world contemplating impermanence in all
conditioned phenomena and he has the
perception of death well-established
eternally internally these five things
with when developed and cultivated need
exclusive excuse me to disenchantment to
dispassion cessation these technology
and this is a game pollutant and what an
under is the perception of
unattractiveness here a bhikkhu who have
used this body upward from the soles of
the feet and downward from the tips of
the hairs enclosed in skin as full of
meneka as full of many kinds of
impurities they are in this body hair
the head his body nails teeth skin flesh
sinews bone bone marrow kidneys heart
liver spleen lungs intestines stomach
excrement barf and ass blood sweat tears
grease love it's not fluid joints in
Europe thus he dwells concentrating on
attracts from the body in the body this
is called the procession of
unattractiveness yes so this is in
regard to super meditation meditation on
the unattractiveness
and you said yesterday you're talking
about it he said that's establishing
one's mind on the tsuba and then making
it injury without losing sight of the
peripheral of that a tsuba
even when sensual information is present
internally externally well it comes down
to the main point of that is basically
you cannot be attracted and repelled by
the same thing at the same time so if
that which attracts you he tells you
then you'll be repelled the attractive
the attraction will since so that's
important thing to realize because when
you read out the bit from a good
training car or if the buddha recommends
like reviewing your body terms of what
is made up it's very easy to do that
wrongly in a sense of you keep bringing
the new things new objects of your
perceptions into your mind and then
trying to kind of
sort of generate a sense of disgust
dispassion but the thing is the point is
not to find things that are disgusting
as a replacement to things that are
attractive the point is to see things
that are attractive is underlined by a
disgusting things by things that are
repelling by things that are non
attractive so you need to see they're
simultaneously present they're just on a
different level because it's easily you
can easily force yourself to not look at
the the attractive and just focus on
unattractive but sooner or later when
you're tired when your mindfulness
lapses when attractive arises again you
have no no no protection against it
because all you are used to is doing the
like sort of replacing it and pushing it
away and getting there the non
attractive because you were told that's
what you need to do well actually the
one ever said you need to replace it you
say you need to see it you need to see
it in relation to that which is
attractive so when you're reviewing your
body for example to get that sense of
this passion because it's all the other
organs all of the organs by themselves
are not they're quite quite repulsive
actually and certainly non attractive so
that's that's that's easily seen but
what it's hard to see is that when you
are attracted either towards gaining
physical pleasure towards pursuing the
objects of physical pleasure externally
you want to see that all of those
experiences of sensuality basically is
fundamentally inseparable from these
disgusting organs and fundamentally
established upon them so they can never
be apart from them they can never be
independent of the repulsive repulsive
foundations which means they themselves
can never be really truly attractive so
a person who is truly experienced this
passion and developed it for them things
are very dispassionate and maybe
slightly less dispassionate or rather
very unattractive and slightly less
unattractive sensuality the beautiful
things become slightly less unattractive
so you can still recognize the beauty
but none of it is the attractive Beauty
they would induce
exactly so it's ugly and less ugly yeah
comes down to that not like ugly and
beautiful that you're just trying to
kind of revolve around but you know in
order to see the the beautiful is ugly
is you need to see that it's
simultaneously and it separately bound
up with those repulsive aspects that are
kind of inseparable from inescapable
so that's what once once the man is
experienced through this passion that
order of which comes first ugly or
beautiful cannot be changed anymore the
beautiful cannot step outside of ugly
ever again and assume its own you know
privileged kind of sensual existence
that's how sensuality ceases as well
when it becomes fully enclosed in ugly
and you lose entire dispersion for any
aspect of sensuality conceivable
possible because in its nature you've
seen it it's just inconceivable without
the basis of ugly and as such it's ugly
in itself unattractive or repulsive you
see the danger in sensuality you have to
the danger in sensuality you have to
then say you're going to see the danger
in the danger becomes apparent once this
passion has been developed otherwise you
can't grasp the danger but once you
experience this passion and the mind is
truly sort of withdrawn from the
perversion of perception which is what
sensuality is perceiving and ugly is
beautiful and he sees it for what it is
ugly and just slightly less ugly but
equally not wanted then you recognize
wow what a danger it is to actually keep
focusing on the less ugly regarding is
beautiful because it keeps you bound to
the entire thing that is subject to this
this complete annihilation eventually
sickness aging and death and then Ryo
repeats and again and again and again
just because of that tiny little
perversion just because of your tiny
little assumption in thinking that
sensual the beautiful objects of senses
can exist separate from the repulsive
non-attractive disgusting foundations
where they are
so that's why it's important not to keep
contemplating the repulsive kind of
before or after or trying to replace you
if the beautiful sensual thoughts with
it you want to see them so you need to
contemplate but you need to see it at
the same time so yes think about the
repulsive things of the body so that you
can experience this passion but then you
have to apply or rather maintain that
this passion that I said to a perception
must learn how to endure even with
sensuality arises whereby you don't just
jump on some salt and try to get rid of
it because there wasn't your doing to
begin with what you're doing is whether
you choose to abandon attending the
foundations of that sensuality and give
to rise to attending pleasing and like
temporary sort of particular features of
it which is basically how sensual
essential thoughts originate and yet
they get maintained so the owner you
don't keep replacing sensuality you want
to see through it
so all of those things that are
disgusting contemplations and so on that
the Buddha was encouraging amongst to do
need to be seen through the sensual to
the beautiful objects through the
beautiful things not instead
you're not saying that once you go in
try seek out beautiful sights
oh no well if you if you are seeking out
the will size means there is no
establishment of the right that means
the perception is already perverted
which means the mind is not seeing not
attending to the roots of dispassion
roots of disgusting aspects of that
sensuality because you don't you don't
need to you need to restrain the senses
first fully stop giving into the habit
of seeking pleasure by default for these
roots to be able to be seen through the
reason sensual prosperity in a form of
thought or a possibility or intention
but if your intention habitually do to
be needed to give in to the action by
our senses and see how the pleasure the
whole amount of transparency in through
it will be possible because you just you
just went off went off with it
so yeah that sometimes people think I
must expose myself sensual to prove but
if you need to prove to yourself that
you're free from some salty means you
don't know it means you doubt it which
means you're not free if the doubt can
enter it there is no freedom there and
in the same sense in order to be able to
seek sensuality even as a proof it
requires perversion of perception it
require central perceptions to be
established which means if even if
you're seeking out to prove it yourself
means you're seeking out of sensuality
[Music] so no seeking out seeking out whatsoever
so no seeking out seeking out whatsoever
and then seeing through whatever to
present however its present however
beautiful it might be you see it
inseparable from those ugly aspects that
you have been contemplating
because they are there because the
sensuality the sensual beauty is
actually ugly and disgusting and
inseparable from disgusting things
unattractive things that's where freedom
comes in Charlotte is possible if it
were true truly beautifully beautiful
and independent you wouldn't be able to
but then it wouldn't be a problem either
you won't have together but it's not
truly beautiful it's a mistake based on
ignorance based of sensual craving based
on the fire of lust and so on so that's
why it's a problem that's why pleasure
underlined by craving is a problem
pleasure without underlying cravings is
not a problem but there is no central
pleasure that it's not underlined by
mode by desire for more lasting
ingredient